Register of the John O. Koehler papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Stasi Research Material, 1931-2002.; 19.97 linear feet (Box 1-8, 18-50, 52-57)
  - Federal Republic of Germany Files, 1990-1998.; 4.59 linear feet (Box 29-39)
    - BF informiert: Kurs auf die entwickelte Diktatur Die Neuausrichtung des Staatssicherheitsdienstes 1956/57 (BF), 1995 (Folder 38: 4)
    - Anatomie der Staatssicherheit, 1995 (Folder 38: 5-7)
    - Zentrale Ermittlungsstelle Regierungs- und Vereinigungskriminalität (ZERV), 1995-1996 (Folder 38: 8)
    - Der Beitrag des Arbeitsgebietes I der DDR-Kriminalpolizei zur politischen Überwachung und Repression, 1996 (Folder 38: 9)
    - BF informiert: "Gegen das Volk kann nichts mehr entschieden werden." MfS und SED im Bezirk Neubrandenburg (BF no. 12), 1996 (Folder 38: 10)
    - BF informiert: "Unsere Nerven lagen allmählich blank." MfS und SED in Halle (BF no.13), 1996 (Folder 38: 11)
    - BF informiert: Partisanen des Kalten Krieges (BF no. 14), 1996 (Folder 38: 12)
    - BF informiert: "Hat nicht wenigstens die Stasi die Stimmung im Lande gekannt?" MfS und SED im Bezirk Karl-Marx-Stadt (BF no. 19), 1997 (Folder 38: 13)
    - List of trials, 1997 (Folder 38: 14)
    - Investigation of DDR Government crimes, 1990-1998 (Folder 39: 1-4)
  - United States Government Documents, 1943-1997.; 1.67 linear feet (Box 40-43)
    Correspondence, reports, and photocopies obtained via FOIA request from various U.S. government agencies including the Army, Air Force, Navy, FBI and CIA. Includes documents regarding the Stasi, terrorism, defectors, and the Cold War.
    - Communist infiltration of U.S. Military, 1943-1955 (Folder 40: 1-2)
    - CIC - NKVD Liaison, 1945-1953 (Folder 40: 3)
    - Operation Bingo, 1946 (Folder 40: 4)
    - Abductions, 1947-1951 (Folder 40: 5)
    - Defectors - Stephen Wechsler, 1952-1953 (Folder 40: 6-7)
    - U.S. Penetration of East German Government, 1953 (Folder 40: 8)
    - Defectors - Robert Blevens, 1953-1995 (Folder 40: 9-13)
    - Defectors from the U.S. Army, 1956-1995 (Folder 41: 1-9)
    - International Terrorism in 1978, 1979 (Folder 42: 1)
    - Reports on terrorism, 1982-1983 (Folder 42: 2)
    - Report of the Vice President's Task Force on Combatting Terrorism, 1986 (Folder 42: 3)
    - Senate Intelligence reports, 1986-1988 (Folder 42: 4)
    - Air Force spies, 1988 (Folder 42: 5-6)
    - Michael Peri, 1989-1990 (Folder 42: 7)
    - Recent espionage cases, 1990 (Folder 42: 8)
    - Senate Intelligence reports, 1990-1994 (Folder 42: 9)
    - U.S. Military defectors to East Germany, 1992 (Folder 42: 10)
    - Americans Who Spied Against their Country since World War II, 1992 (Folder 42: 11)
    - JPRS Report: Terrorism, 1994 (Folder 42: 12)
    - Senate Intelligence Report - Aldrich Ames, 1994 (Folder 43: 1)
    - Conference on Cold War Military Records and History, 1994 (Folder 43: 2-5)
    - Criminal Complaint against James Michael Clark, 1997 (Folder 43: 6-7)
    - East German agents, undated (Folder 43: 8)
  - Interviews and Broadcasts, 1990-1997; 1.5 linear feet (Box 44-46)
    Includes transcripts, audiotapes and videotapes regarding the Stasi. Videotapes include news broadcasts and documentaries about the Stasi and Erich Mielke. Audiotapes record interviews conducted by Koehler in the course of his research. Interviewees include Stasi victims, former officers, German government officials, and Joachim Gauck.
    - Rainer Wiegand Transcript, 1991 February (Folder 44: 1-5)
    - Rainer Wiegand Transcript, 1991-1996 (Folder 44: 6)
    - Dissident Interviews - Horst Erdmann, 1962-1994. (Folder 44: 7)
    - Dissident Interviews - Horst Erdmann, 1964-1997 (Folder 44: 8-9)
    - Dissident Interviews - Peter Gauweiler, Ralf Hirsch, Simon Wiesenthal, Heiner Sauer, and Joachim Gauck, 1991 (Folder 44: 10)
    - Transcripts - Peter Gauweiler, Rupert Scholz, Heiner Sauer, Ralf Hirsch, and Joachim Gauck, 1991 (Folder 44: 11)
    - Heinz Busch Transcript, 1992 July (Folder 44: 12)
    - Interview with Colonel Rainer Wiegand on personnel and kidnapping, audiocassette, 1991 February 5 (Box 45)
      Access
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012607
    - Interview with Colonel Rainer Wiegand on terrorism, audiocassette, 1991 February 7 (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012628
    - Interview with Colonel Rainer Wiegand on kidnapping, top secret cases and mysterious deaths, audiocassette, 1991 February 6 (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012621
    - Interview with Colonel Wiegand on Pfotenhauer murder and international terrorism, audiocassette, 1991 February 7 (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012632
    - Interview with Colonel Rainer Wiegand on terrorism and murder, audiocassette, 1991 February 7 (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012648
    - Interview with dissident Ralf Hirsch, audiocassette, 1991 September 22 (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012649
    - Interviews with Horst Erdmann and Colonel Wolfgang Koch, audiocassette, 1991 September (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012651
    - Interviews with Simon Wiesenthal, Prosecutor Heiner Sauer, and Ruediger Knechtel, audiocassette, 1991 October (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012652
    - Interview with former Stasi Lieutenant Roland Weihrich and Discussion between victims and Stasi officers, audiocassette, 1991 October (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012699
    - Interviews with Karl Grossman and Josef Kneifel, audiocassette, 1991 October (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012655
    - Interview with Karl Grossman, audiocassette, 1991 November (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012664
    - Interviews with Colonel Manfred Kleinpeter and Karl Grossman on HVA, audiocassette, 1991-1994 (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012665
    - Interview with Colonel Heinz Busch on HVA, audiocassette, 1992 February 28 (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012676
    - Interview with Colonel Franz Ross, audiocassette, 1992 July (Box 45)
      Koehler conducted this interview over the telephone. At times the sound quality is poor due to telephone noise and tape hiss from the cassette.
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012677
    - Interviews with Dr. Wagner and Dr. William Stearman, audiocassette, 1997 June (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012680
    - Interview with Captain Schachtschneider, audiocassette, undated (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012681
    - Interview with Professor Jakob Segal, audiocassette, undated (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012692
    - Interview with Colonel Rainer Wiegand on Labelle bombing and CIA recruitment attempt, audiocassette, undated (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012686
    - Interview with Colonel Rainer Wiegand on CIA recruitment and operations against US Embassy, audiocassette, undated (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012687
    - Interview with Colonel Rainer Wiegand on counterintelligence, audiocassette, undated (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012701
    - Interviews with Professor Rupert Scholz, constitutional expert and Horst Erdmann, former Stasi prisoner, audiocassette, undated (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012693
    - Interviews with Peter Gauweiler and Horst Erdman, audiocassette, undated (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012700
    - Interview with Joachim Gauck and discussion between victims and Stasi officers, audiocassette, undated (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012654
    - Interviews with Colonel Rainer Wiegand and Colonel A. Teferry, microcassette, undated (Box 45)
      Use copy reference number: 2001c75_a_0012703
    - Stasi, 3 videocassettes, undated (Box 46)
      West German documentary made for training domestic counterintelligence officers
    - Hall Sting, videocassette, undated (Box 46)
    - Hall Incident news reports, videocassette, undated (Box 46)
    - Hall Case, videocassette, undated (Box 46)
    - Mielke, videocassette, undated. (Box 46)
      German documentary
    - Mielke, 2 videocassettes, undated. (Box 46)
      German format
  - Subject Files, 1931-2002.; 7.71 linear feet (Box 1-8, 48-50, 52-57)
    Contains clippings, notes, and printed material related to Koehler's research. Documents East German repression of its citizens, terrorism, counterintelligence, international relations, and dissidents. Several broad topics (identified by the archivist) are present in the files: international espionage and counterespionage, general Stasi operations, surveillance and repression, terrorism, reunification, and printed materials.
    Original subject order was maintained during processing, though folders with similar titles have been grouped to aid research.
    - General Stasi Operations
      - Officers, 1990-1992 (Folder 10: 1)
      - Personnel, 1961-1991 (Folder 10: 2)
      - Staff lists, 1989 (Folder 10: 3)
      - Staff lists, 1991 (Folder 10: 4)
      - MfS internal life, 1957-1992 (Folder 10: 5)
      - MfS structure, 1990-1991 (Folder 10: 6)
      - Economics, 1968-1997 (Folder 10: 7-8)
      - Koko (Commercial Coordination), 1951-1997 (Folder 10: 9-12)
      - Communist money, 1993-1996 (Folder 10: 13)
      - Technical service, 1990-1996 (Folder 11: 1)
      - German character traits - communist resurgence, 1991-1994 (Folder 11: 2)
      - Wiegand protocol, 1991 (Folder 11: 3)
      - Erich Mielke indictment, 1934 (Folder 11: 4-6)
      - Erich Mielke, 1931-1997 (Folder 11: 7-11)
      - Erich Mielke, 1989-1995 (Folder 12: 1-2)
      - Unsorted clippings, 1944-1997 (Folder 12: 3-7)
    - International Espionage and Counterespionage
      - HVA, undated (Folder 12: 8)
      - HVA, 1965-1995 (Folder 12: 9)
      - HVA - disinformation and forgeries, 1965-1994 (Folder 12: 10)
      - Miscellaneous MfS/Wolf, 1974-1997 (Folder 12: 11-12)
      - Markus Wolf, 1987-1996 (Folder 12: 13)
      - Markus Wolf, 1989-1997 (Folder 13: 1-3)
      - Markus Wolf trial, 1993-1997 (Folder 13: 4)
      - Kidnap/alligator case, 1951-1996 (Folder 13: 5-6)
      - Mail robberies, 1991-1996 (Folder 13: 7)
      - Weapons smuggling, 1991 (Folder 13: 8)
      - OiBEs (Deep Cover Agents), 1989-1997 (Folder 13: 9-10)
      - KGB, 1949-1995 (Folder 13: 11-14)
      - Invasion of West Germany - Stasi's role, 1960 (Folder 13: 15)
      - Invasion of West Berlin, 1992-1995 (Folder 13: 16)
      - NVA-HVA, undated (Folder 14: 1)
      - KVP-NVA, undated (Folder 14: 2)
      - Espionage, undated (Folder 14: 3)
      - Espionage, 1961-1997 (Folder 14: 4-10)
      - Stasi in West Germany, 1959-1991 (Folder 14: 11)
      - Espionage versus West Germany, 1960-1997 (Folder 14: 12-13)
      - Espionage versus West Germany, 1961-1996 (Folder 15: 1-3)
      - Günther Guillaume, 1955-1995 (Folder 15: 4-9)
      - Willy Brandt, 1990-1996 (Folder 15: 10)
      - Western services, 1967-1994 (Folder 16: 1)
      - Eastern Europe, 1974-1995 (Folder 16: 2)
      - Defense (NATO), 1966-1967 (Folder 16: 3)
      - Espionage versus NATO, 1993 (Folder 16: 4)
      - Espionage against the U.S., 1993 (Folder 16: 5-9)
      - Africa analyses, 1991-1997 (Folder 16: 10)
      - Africa and Latin America, 1980-1990 (Folder 16: 11)
      - Chile, 1976-1998 (Folder 16: 12)
      - Aldrich Ames, 1994-1995 (Folder 17: 1-2)
      - Wolfgang Krase, 1984-1985 (Folder 17: 3)
      - Elly Rometsch, 1964-1965 (Folder 17: 4)
      - Klaus Kuron, 1984-1992 (Folder 17: 5)
      - Uwe Barschel, 1994-1995 (Folder 17: 6)
      - Hans Kemritz, 1952-1990 (Folder 17: 7)
      - Espionage - Carney and Thompson, 1965-1992 (Folder 17: 8)
      - Suarez case, 1955-1992 (Folder 17: 9-11)
      - Horst Hesse, 1956-1975 (Folder 17: 12)
      - Rosenberg spy ring, 1992 (Folder 17: 13)
    - Surveillance and Repression
      - Oppression, 1958-1996 (Folder 47: 1-4)
      - Informants, 1988-1997 (Folder 47: 5-9)
      - Wiegand paper on informants, undated (Folder 47: 10)
      - Concentration camps, 1984-1993 (Folder 47: 11)
      - DKP - secret army, 1990-1996 (Folder 47: 12)
      - Election fraud, 1991-1996 (Folder 47: 13)
      - Herbert Wehner, 1991-1996 (Folder 47: 14)
      - 1953 uprising, 1990-1995 (Folder 47: 15)
      - Generals for Peace, 1993 (Folder 47: 16)
      - Nazis and Neo-Nazis, 1946-1992 (Folder 47: 17-18)
      - CharitÉ Hospital, 1990-1991 (Folder 48: 1)
      - Intellectuals, 1992-1996 (Folder 48: 2-3)
      - Dissidents - Jürgen Fuchs, 1991-1995 (Folder 48: 4)
      - Defectors, 1959-1992 (Folder 48: 5-6)
      - Opposition and victims' groups, 1993-1997 (Folder 48: 7)
      - Electronic surveillance, 1976-1987 (Folder 48: 8)
      - Surveillance of politicians, 1991-1992 (Folder 48: 9)
      - Berlin Wall, undated (Folder 48: 10)
      - Building the Wall, 1991 (Folder 48: 11)
      - Escapes - Berlin Wall, 1961-1965 (Folder 48: 12-13)
      - Murder, 1987-1997 (Folder 48: 14)
      - Murder, 1987-1997 (Folder 49: 1-2)
      - Murder/Executions, 1961-1997 (Folder 49: 3-4)
      - Scheithauer Murder, 1963-1991 (Folder 49: 5)
    - Terrorism
      - Terrorism, 1979-1997 (Folder 49: 6-13)
      - Terrorism, 1981-1996 (Folder 50: 1)
      - Red Army Faction, 1985-1997 (Folder 50: 2-4)
      - International terrorism, 1979-1991 (Folder 50: 5-6)
      - Arabs/La Belle, 1969-1997 (Folder 50: 7-11)
      - Future danger, 1990-1994 (Folder 50: 12)
    - Reunification
      - End of DDR, 1989-1998 (Folder 51: 1-4)
      - Reunification and politics, 1990-1997 (Folder 52: 5-6)
      - Reunification, 1989-1999 (Folder 53: 1-9)
      - Retribution/Spitzel, 1990-1996 (Folder 53: 10)
      - SED, 1990-1991 (Folder 53: 11)
      - Erich Honecker, 1990-1995 (Folder 54: 1-2)
      - Trials, 1991-1997 (Folder 54: 3)
      - Revenge and trials, 1991-1997 (Folder 54: 4)
      - Opening Stasi files, 1991-1996 (Folder 54: 5)
      - Wolfgang Vogel, 1992-1996 (Folder 54: 6)
      - Karl Wienand, 1996 (Folder 54: 7)
    - Published material
      - Western European Union Brief on the Berlin Question, 1961 (Folder 54: 8)
      - Assorted pamphlets, 1971-1995 (Folder 54: 9)
      - International Security Review, 1982 (Folder 54: 10)
      - Freiheitsglocke, 1985-1990 (Folder 54: 11-15)
      - Freiheitsglocke, 1991-1997 (Folder 55: 1-6)
      - Kalter Krieg als antikommunistischer Widerstand, 1987 (Folder 55: 7-8)
      - Combatting Terrorism: A Matter of Leverage, 1986 (Folder 55: 9)
      - Berliner Illustrierte, 1989 (Folder 55: 10)
      - Grenzfall, 1989 (Folder 55: 11)
      - Der Spiegel, 1989-1990 (Folder 55: 12-13)
      - Der Spiegel, 1990 (Folder 56: 1)
      - Der Spiegel series, 1990 (Folder 56: 2)
      - Der Spiegel, series, undated (Folder 56: 3-4)
      - Dresden by Hans Kromer, 1990 (Folder 56: 5)
      - Aus Politik und Zeitgeschichte, 1990-1993 (Folder 56: 6)
      - Conference on European Security and Cooperation, 1990 (Folder 56: 7)
      - Dateline, 1990 (Folder 56: 8)
      - Politische Studien, 1992 (Folder 56: 9)
      - Die Mauer Spricht, 1992 (Folder 56: 10)
      - Cold War International History Project Bulletin, 1992-1997 (Folder 56: 11-14)
      - Ulbricht and the Concrete "Rose,", 1993 (Folder 57: 1)
      - News of Intelligence and Counterintelligence, 1993. (Folder 57: 2)
        In Russian
      - Social Democrats as Victims in the Fight against the Red Dictatorship, 1994 (Folder 57: 3)
      - Der Stacheldraht, 1994-1997 (Folder 57: 4-5)
      - Deutschland Archiv, 1995 (Folder 57: 6)
      - Mauern-Gitter-Stacheldraht, 1996 (Folder 57: 7)
      - Compromise, Collaboration, and Betrayal: the Legacy of the Czech Secret Police Cadre, 1997 (Folder 57: 8)
      - Initiativgruppe Lager Mühlberg, 1997 (Folder 57: 9)
      - Hilferufe von drüben, 1997 (Folder 57: 10)
      - Einsatzkommandos an der unsichtbaren Front, 1999 (Folder 57: 11)
      - Die Zusammenarbeit zwischen dem Ministerium für Staatssicherheit der DDR (MfS) und dem Ministerium des Innern Kubas (MININT), 2002 (Folder 57: 12)
- Incremental materials (Box 59-78)